In the last couple of lessons, we've
looked at how we can
use query augmentation and cross-encoder
re-ranking to improve
retrieval results.
In this lesson, I'm going to show
you how we can use user
feedback about the
relevancy of retrieved
results to automatically
improve the performance
of the retrieval
system using a
technique called embedding
adapters.
Let me show you how it works.
Embedding adapters are a
way to alter the
embedding of a query
directly in order to
produce better retrieval results.
In effect, we insert an
additional stage in
the retrieval system
called an embedding adapter,
which happens after
the embedding model,
but before we retrieve
the most relevant results.
We train the embedding
adapter using user feedback
on the relevancy of
our retrieved results for
a set of queries.
Let's get into it.
So the first thing we do is grab
our helper functions as before.
One special thing here is we're
going to need Torch because we're going
to effectively train a model, but a
very lightweight one.
And we create
our embedding function
and load everything into Corma.
And again,
we project all of our data.
So the first thing we need
for this approach is a data set.
We don't
have one ready because we haven't really
had users using our
RAG application.
But we can use a model
to generate a data set for us.
And once again, this is all about
creating the right prompt.
So we're going to use GPT again. And
essentially, we're prompting
the model as an expert, helpful financial
research assistant. And it
should suggest 10 to 15 short
questions that are
important to ask when analyzing an
annual report and with some guidelines
about what the
output should be like.
And this will generate some queries
that users might actually have run
against our system.
So let's
ask it to generate those queries.
We see that these
are fairly reasonable questions
to ask about any company's
financial statements.
So we're
going to get the results from Chrome.
And what we're going to do, and we'll get
the retrieved documents associated
with the results.
And what we're going to do is
also ask the model
to evaluate the results. In
a real RAG system, you
can easily ask your
users to give a thumbs up or thumbs
down on the generated output, and
then reference that with the retrieved
results to give a signal about
what results were
actually relevant and
which weren't. In this case, we don't
quite have that, but we can
use a model to evaluate the relevancy of
the retrieved results for
each query. And again, this
is just
about prompting the model.
So we're going to ask our helpful expert
financial assistant to
tell us whether a given statement
is relevant to the given query.
And we're going to ask it to output
only yes or no. And then
we're going to
essentially transform yes to
one's and no to
negative one's. And I'll explain why in just a
minute, but that's the prompt. And then
what we're going to do
is we are going to get our retrieved
embeddings and our query
embeddings.
And we're going to start making
a dataset to train
our embedding adapter.
And the way we're
going to do it is like this.
We're going to have our
adapter query embeddings, adapter
doc embeddings, and
our adapter labels.
Now the adapter prefix just means we're
going to use this in a dataset. They're
not special in any way. they're just
the embeddings of our queries
and the embeddings of
our documents. The labels we're
going to get from our evaluation model,
the label is going
to be plus one or minus one depending
on whether the document
is relevant or not
to the given query.
So we're just going to loop
over everything to create these triples.
So the model is
performing an evaluation for us.
Now it's
no mistake that our labels are
plus one and minus one, because
what we're going
to do when when we're training our
embedding adapter model
is use these
values as our loss function for
cosine distance.
When two vectors are identical,
the cosine similarity
between them is one.
When two vectors are opposite,
the cosine similarity between
them is negative one.
In other words,
we want relevant results
to point in the
same direction as vectors,
and we want irrelevant results to
point in the
opposite direction from
a given query.
And this is the model that we're
going to train.
That's exactly what it's going
to try to do.
All right, and let's
check out the length of our data set.
Great, 150.
So that's
15 queries with 10 results each, each
one labeled for relevancy.
So the next thing we need to do,
because we're using Torch to train
our embedding adopter,
is we need to
transform our data set
into a Torch tensor data set.
So we're just going to do
some data manipulation here
to transform these into
Torch tensor types. And
finally, we're going
to pack everything into a
Torch data set.
So let's
set up our embedding adapter model.
The first thing is to
set up the model itself,
and the model
is fairly straightforward.
It takes as input a query embedding,
a document embedding,
and an adapter matrix. We compute an
updated query embedding
by multiplying our
original query embedding
by the adapter matrix, and then we
compute the cosine
similarity between our
updated query embedding
and our document embedding. Next,
let's define our loss function.
Again,
our loss takes a query embedding,
document embedding, adapter matrix,
and label. And we run the model
to compute the cosine similarity,
and we compute the mean squared
error between the
cosine similarity and the label.
And you'll notice again that
the plus one label means that
the cosine similarity
says that the
vectors are pointing in the same
direction, and a negative one
label means they should be pointing
in the opposite direction. In
this way, we want our queries to
be pointing in the
same direction as relevant
documents, and
in the opposite direction
to irrelevant documents. And
this is what we're training
our adapter matrix to do. We initialize
our adapter matrix
for training. You might
recognize this is very
similar to a linear
layer in a traditional
neural network. And that's
really all we're doing.
Next, let's
set up our training loop. We
set our minimum loss and
our best matrix as things
to keep track of. Let's train
for 100 epochs.
For each query embedding,
document embedding,
and label in our Torch data set,
we compute our loss.
If the loss that
we computed is better
than our previous loss,
We will keep track of that
as the best matrix so far.
And then we back propagate.
And let's run our training loop.
And you can see it's very, very
fast, because again, this
is exactly the same
thing as if we were training a single
linear layer of a
traditional neural network. So
let's take a look at the best
loss that we got.
This is pretty good. A loss of 0.5
is pretty good. It means we've got
pretty much a halfway
improvement in terms of
where we started from.
So one thing we'd like to take a look
at as how the adapter
matrix influences our query vector.
To do that, we
can construct a test vector
consisting of all ones, and
we can multiply that test
vector by our best matrix. And
what this will tell us is which dimensions
of our vectors get
scaled by what amount. You
can think of an embedding adapter
as stretching space
and squeezing space for the dimensions
which are most
relevant to the
particular queries that we have while
reducing the dimensions
that are not relevant to our
query. You'll also notice that it can
reverse dimensions.
So let's plot what that looks like.
And here you can see how
each dimension of our test vector,
which consists only of ones,
has been stretched and squeezed.
Some have been elongated a lot,
while others have been
made to be almost zero.
And so what this
means is our embedding
adapter has basically decided, okay,
these dimensions are more relevant,
these are less relevant.
These are actually opposite
to the things that we want to find,
and these things are actually
more relevant to the things
that we want to find.
Now let's take a look at
what effect this actually
has on our queries.
So let's do as we did before. We'll take
our generated queries and
embed them, and let's compute also
our adapted query embeddings, and then
we project them.
Now let's
plot what we get against our dataset.
And as you can see,
our original queries
were quite scattered around,
but our new queries concentrate in
a certain part of the dataset
which is most relevant to our
queries. You can see how the red
queries have been
adapted through the
embedding adapter to
transform them into
the green queries,
to push them into a
particular part of the space.
So as you can see,
an embedding adapter is a simple
but powerful technique
for customizing query
embeddings to your
specific application.
In order to make this work,
you need to collect a dataset,
either a synthetic one like the one we've
generated here, or else one that's based
on user data. User data
usually works best
because it actually
means that people are using your
retrieval system for
their specific tasks. Again, because
this
approach involves prompting and
because it involves the
use of a large
language model, it's worth experimenting
with the prompts and
it's also worth experimenting with different initializations
of the adapter
matrix.
Even maybe consider using a full
lightweight neural network
and training that instead of a
simple matrix instead.
You might want to tune the
hyperparameters of the
embedding adapter training
process or you might want to
collect more specific data and try
this out with
a specific application
in mind rather than our very
general one of trying to understand
a financial statement.
In the next lesson we'll cover some other
techniques which are just now emerging
from research to
improve embedding-based retrieval
systems.